Abraham: A cyber security incident
log is a short document created and
maintained by cyber security professionals
that indicates most of the relevant
information about a security incident.
Nicole: Drawing information from
Cyber security log files can be
instrumental in mitigating attacks
and re-establishing a system.
Abraham: The more up to date a log is the
easier it is for the cyber security team
to understand the risks and to be able
to act quickly to mitigate an attack.
It also provides audit trails
for tracking elements, processes
or users involved in an attack.
Nicole: In large organisations there
is often a huge volume of different
events that need to be logged from
minor incidents such as compromised
credentials, for example lost ID cards,
to network applications and operating
systems and other infrastructure elements
that generate their own event logs.
This data can help teams to
profile typical networking and user
activities, therefore making it
easier to spot suspicious activity
that stands out and this can help
logs become an early warning system.
Abraham: There can be serious
legal implications related to
not keeping timely incident logs,
such as large fines or lawsuits.
GDPR and the ‘Network Information
Systems Regulations of 2018’ require
organisations to report any high-risk
breaches within 72 hours of discovery.
Up to date incident logs can also help to
reassure stakeholders that an organisation
works hard to maintain control of its
cyber security responsibilities to
prevent breaches and loss of data.
Nicole: So, what other steps
should be included within a cyber
security incident response plan?
As we have already discussed
previously the incident response
lifecycle is broken down into phases:
• Abraham: Preparation
• Detection and Analysis
• Containment
• Eradication
• and Recovery; and Post-Event Activity.
Nicole: Whereas an incident
response plan is more like a set
of instructions to follow which
according to the NCSC should include:
Abraham: Key Contacts- these may include
contacts from a range of different
areas including the IR team and others
such as the legal department, senior
management and HR, but as incidents
can happen anytime and often anywhere
within an organization, they should
always take into consideration
the availability of the contacts.
Nicole: This should always be kept up
to date and take into consideration
holidays and out of hours contacts
and there should be at least one
conference number, which is always
available for urgent incident calls.
Abraham: Escalation criteria and the
process for making critical decisions
such as when to escalate the situation
to include key decision makers.
Having a flowchart, checklist or
traffic light system, can help determine
the next steps to be taken, related
to priority and potential severity.
Nicole: A Basic Flowchart or
process should cover the full
incident lifecycle including
preparation, detection and analysis,
response, recovery and follow up.
Abraham: Basic guidance on legal and
regulatory requirements with details of
when to engage legal support or HR and
guidelines on how to capture evidence
and contact the regulatory authorities.
Nicole: To further enhance a plan,
it should contain a checklist to help
teams to organise themselves at each
stage of the plan and can be used
easily in an emergency and could include
forms for documenting and tracking
incidents and post incident reviews.
Abraham: It would also benefit by
providing guidance on responding
to various incidents and how
to remediate and recover.
So why is it important to have an IR plan?
Not having a plan would make it difficult
for security teams to know what to do
or how to respond to any incidents.
This could cause a delay and in turn
lead to more significant damage.
Nicole: Having an IR plan enables
teams at all levels to respond quickly,
following clearly defined guidelines
to help safeguard any data and systems.
It also offers solutions to
mitigating responses and guidelines on
collecting and analysing information
to help prevent future attacks.
Abraham: And finally, it helps everyone
to identify their role in the process and
knowing when to and who to escalate the
incident to, which in turn can prevent
unauthorised actions taking place.